[Music]
Heat. Heat.
Hello everybody. Good evening, good day
and welcome to all of you to the Ask
Abilit show. Today we are doing episode
242 and I'm going to take questions that
you all have asked in the comments a
bunch of those and then if there's time
I'll take questions from the live chat
as well. Before that let's see who all
is there on the live stream. I can see
plenty of people. I can see Manu Krishna
Oscar Madison feminist slayer Matias
Vandal Berg from Belgium Rahul Dunake
Manu Krishna Krishna Ragunat from the
Surinamese Netherlands Mr. 88ers P Ain
Nishal Nishal Ray Shri Ramchandra
uh the priest of
Vanasi Rahul Dunak Info King info King
who else do we have Rushab Singh Kumar
Patel Sai Sai Sasang Bharata Edits chat
DSP Bishal Patro D KLC28 Samati Ravi
Prasad Bushan Priyanka Javalia Prexen
Aratim Roy Shri Watsa Shriatza Shubam
Jane
Aish Mishra Kiadi the Chad Vishnari
Shesh Chri Jal Ra Sam Achara nationalist
fam boy Rashmir Matop Pareth from Texas
Sumana Gosh Official Deep Debbakar World
Manu Krishna Tjas B Sergeant Skylan
Daddy of Diddi Rash God Illuminati Creek
Kuml Mclovin
Arbhat Rama Krishnan Guru Morti Duv
Jaganath Geopolitical Dub from Indor Mr.
Bin Salman 86 786 Nabarita Das Mr. Jam
Hirkumar Patel and lots and lots and
lots of other people Ken Raf Ritwij
Phenomena Brishnu Muan Mayangati Mr. Jam
and B
uh I lost that. All right. All right.
All right. All right. Welcome to all of
you and thank you so much for being on
the live stream on this live stream with
us. I can see Amisha as well, Sumesh and
many other people. So let's get going
with the questions. Once again, there's
been a lot of questions about Pakistan
because of the situation that's ongoing.
So I'm going to take a bunch of those as
well. Um and yeah, so let's get going
with the the questions that uh we have.
What are the questions? Let's get into
it.
Okay, this is a question by Karan
Nagpal. Okay, Karan Nagpal says, "Humor
me this. Pakistan's total debt, external
debt is $131 billion as per available
data online while India's strategic
forex reserves are close to $700
billion. What if India buys all of
Pakistan's debt and basically buys out
Pakistan to make it a sort of colony
colony just like China does? uh China
tries to do so with other smaller
nations. This will already save us
billions of dollars in army expenditure
and help us stabilize the border. A
friendly or vasal Pakistan will also
open land routes to central and west
Asia, boosting overall economic strength
of North India. Overall sounds like a
good investment. Is this the right way
to look at things? Well, that's an
interesting question. It's an
interesting thought experiment and I'm
glad that people are thinking in
creative ways.
So what so what if we do this? So yeah
according to the latest uh information
let's assume that Pakistan's external
debt is about $131 billion. Okay. So we
so here's the thought that we as an
India we buy all of that debt and that
turns Pakistan into a Wasab is does can
that work? So we have to understand what
does that $131 billion of debt actually
represent? What does it mean? Is who to
whom does Pakistan owe this? So if you
look at it, there's going to be several
slabs of of debt. First of all, there's
going to be a bunch of debt to
multilateral lenders like the World
Bank, like the Asian Development Bank,
like the International Monetary Fund,
etc. I would say about 30% of Pakistan's
external debt is to these multilateral
lenders, these treaty based organ
institutions. Can India just buy this
debt? No, we can't. Right? It can this
debt that Pakistan owes to these
organizations, institutions etc. It it
cannot be traded like bonds without that
institution's board approval. The World
Bank's board has to approve it. The
IMF's board has to approve it. the Asian
Developments Bank its board has to
approve it and it typically doesn't work
like that. So that 30% we can't buy.
Then there's another slab of debt about
let's say 40%. Which goes to which which
is owed by Pakistan to bilateral
creditors like the Saudis like like like
China like the UAE like Qatar it's been
you know borrowing money from all these
nations. So these are these are
bilateral arrangements. These are
sovereign states. Let's say it's 40%.
Okay. Or that let's say that 40% of
Pakistan's death debt is owed to these
sovereign states. So can India buy this
debt? Potentially yes. But only if the
current lenders agree to
to sell the debt to India. And I can
assure you that Beijing that China will
not agree to sell Pakistan's debt to
India.
Excuse me. So there you have it. So once
again, see 30% IMF, World Bank, all
that. Uh 40% is these sovereign nations,
sovereign states that uh Pakistan owes
money to. Then there'll be about 20% of
of the debt which would be to uh
commercial banks, various global
investors. So theoretically you can
purchase this on the open market. But uh
these investors they if they if they
sense that there's a grab there there's
there's a potential you know opportunity
to to make money uh you're going to have
to buy it at a premium. So 20% of the
debt may you may have to buy it at
double the right the amount like 40%.
You know, so uh so if you look at the
big picture in this manner, then you
will see that at the very most a few
tens of billions of dollars of of of
this debt may be liquid enough for India
to purchase it and you may have to pay
well above the current market value to
to buy this uh debt and let's say so so
practically you can't buy more more than
10 20 30 40 $50 billion of the debt. 50
would be too much, I would say. So, you
can't even buy a third of the
debt. Now, let's say
theoretically we could purchase the the
entirety of the debt. Okay? We we
purchase the whole of the the entire $1
131 billion of debt. Um, so what does it
mean? Does it mean that Pakistan becomes
our Basal state? So you to understand
that debt does not mean the same thing
as
sovereignty. You can own you can own
sovereign bonds of a nation and if you
own those sovereign bonds it it gives
you the right to demand repayment on the
agreed terms on the on the terms of the
sovereign bonds. So let's say you you
have done this then you have the right
to demand repayment from Pakistan. You
don't have the right to tell Pakistan
how to run its army, what to do with its
nukes and what to do with its foreign
policy. You know, for example, let me
give you a great great straightforward
rightway example. China holds about $800
billion of US Treasury bonds. Okay, but
China doesn't govern Washington. China
doesn't is not in position to tell
Washington what to do, right? So um so
you can't even if you purchase all all
of the debt from Pakistan you can't
really control them you can't tell them
what to do and Pakistan if you if India
were to tell Pakistan give us the money
back they would simply default they
would say we are not in a position to
give you the money do what you can yeah
so it's not going to work it will simply
stop payments and it'll dare India to
escalate do what you can right so if you
want to truly vasalize a nation if you
want to truly
control a nation, colonize the nation,
you need boots on the ground, you don't
need bonds, you don't need debt. Okay?
Uh real control historically, even
today, it it requires some form of
either occupation or you need to have
control over very strategic areas of a
country like ports and air u air for um
uh airports, military installations and
all of that. or you need to
install proxy
rulers, okay, which you which you can
see today in various nations. So none of
these things can be delivered by holding
a debt portfolio, right? And at the end
of the day, even if we were to do all
this, would it save billions of dollars
in RB expenditure? Very unlikely. A
Pakistan that is financially beholden to
you but it is still sovereign would
double down on its uh terrorism and
whatever asymmetric tools it it has and
they would create a headache for us. So
I would say it's not going to work even
if we are in a position to buy all of
the debt. We have the money it would
destabilize our economy to some extent
to a certain extent we don't want to do
that and and it's technically
infeasible. So uh so this thought
experiment is is interesting. It's it's
entertaining but I would say it's not a
sound uh it's not a sound investment. Uh
when you own debt it's a financial
claim. It's not something that gives you
sovereignty and uh if you attempt to buy
Pakistan in this manner it would deplete
it would deplete our hard earned
reserves resources etc. It would to some
extent destabilize our economy and it
would most likely not have any effect on
the strategic risk we face from
Pakistan. So not a good
idea. Okay. Surendra Gupta says suppose
you're in power. What would your
response be to the pahilgam
attack? Suppose I'm in power. What would
I do? So yeah, I would give myself I
would I would give myself 10 years to
essentially reduce Pakistan to uh to
atoms. I not to atoms essentially but uh
I would give myself 10 years to have
Pakistan uh essentially break up. So
what would I do? What steps would I
take? First of all, I would take the
step that has been taken the abrogation
or revocation or whatever you want to
call it of the Indis Waters treaty. And
over the next 10 years, I would put the
requisite infrastructure in place so
that after so that by the time the 10
years are out, we are in a position to
completely stop the supply of even a
drop of water to Pakistan. We we should
be in a position to completely dry dry
out the rivers that Pakistan that flow
from India into Pakistan. That's one
thing I would do. So yes, the the
government has taken the right step. now
and and we already have a bunch of
projects, infrastructure projects, the
dams etc that are in various stages of
completion in this region. We need to
double down on that. So I would have
definitely done that. What else would I
have done? Um I would you know what I
would do? I would talk to all the
various multinational corporations that
we have in India. all these companies
like uh you know Coca-Cola, Pepsi,
um Pizza Hut, Domino's, KFC,
uh Apple, all these companies. I'll tell
them you want to do business in India,
you need to shut shop in Pakistan. You
cannot operate in India. If you want to
also operate in Pakistan, choose us. You
you are you are either with us or with
them. You can't be in both places at the
same time. So I would enforce a complete
uh boycott of Pakistan, complete
isolation of Pakistan. I would tell the
world that we our our huge gigantic
market is open for you only if
you stop doing business in Pakistan. I
would tell every single uh sporting
board that if you want to do business
with India, if you want access to the
Indian market, you got to stop doing
business with Pakistan. This involves
cricket also. I would tell every single
cricket board, the ECB, the Australian
board, whoever else there is, if you
want access to the IPL, if you want
access to India, if you want India to uh
do business with you to to play cricket
against you, with you, you got to stop
doing business with Pakistan, you cannot
have a single Pakistani playing in your
big bash league or whatever, whatever
else. That applies to cricket. That
applies to every other sport, every
other event. So I would do everything
that's possible every every lever that I
have. We have tremendous amount of
leverage in India. We we don't realize
it how much we don't realize how much
leverage we have uh by the consequence
of being such a huge market being such a
huge population and and increasingly
becoming a manufacturing power. We have
a tremendous amount of leverage. So I
would enforce the complete isolation of
Pakistan. There will be a few nations
who will want to do business with with
Pakistan. Let them do it. But they
cannot long they can no longer do
business with
us. So I would tighten the squeeze
slowly gradually using all these means.
I would I will give Pakistan no
opportunity to um you know uh start any
any war with India. I would give myself
10 years to completely squeeze isolate
and and finish Pakistan in 10 years. in
10 years it we should be in a position
to stop the the flow of all water to
Pakistan and then let's see what the
economy does and in the next 10 years
obviously our economy needs to grow it
needs to be at least double of what it
is today um hopefully close to a $10
trillion mark and then we'll see from
there so that's what I would do I would
not
uh take recourse to in an emotional
reaction and start bombing Pakistan
maybe maybe a little bit here and there
would would would be okay but I would
not start a war against
Pakistan. Pakistan has been has been
doing this for far too long. They have
they have bled us for decades and it's
time we end the terror terrorist nation.
And of course I would also uh tell
various of our our partners partner
nations who do business with us and who
trade with us and who want access to a
market and so on that you need to stop
harboring Pakistanis on your soil. U if
if we know that various Pakistani
generals and politicians have families
living in the west. I would start
putting a squeeze on that as well. I
would definitely the objective will be
to turn Pakistan into a complete pariah
state. completely isolated state. Um you
know that's that's the
objective. So that's what I would do.
That that's what my response would be.
It would be a cooled calculated long
drawn out response. It would not be an
angry instantaneous response of of
bombing Pakistan and trying to turn
Pakistan to Gaza. There are better ways
of see what what we want to do is we
want to win. We don't want to have
revenge and you know u exalt in in in
temporary revenge. We want long-term
victory. And long-term victory means no
more Pakistan. We want to see Hindu. We
want to see Baluchasthan free. We want
to see Pakunist Pakuna return to
Afghanistan and so on and eventually
long term our border needs to be with
Iran somewhere in the Sindu region. So
that's victory. That is what victory uh
what constitutes victory for me. So I
would give myself 10 years to do these
things and then from there we can take
it forward. That's what I would do. I
would not get all angry and react
emotionally. Okay. Chuching says why did
our Indian government release water from
the dam after suspending the Indis water
treaty? That's a good question. So we
suspend or abrogate or whatever the term
is. we we suspend let's say the industry
which means that now we we don't no
longer um are required to let water flow
into Pakistan right that's what we have
done and then apparently the news comes
out especially from Pakistan that we are
releasing large quantities of water into
Pakistan what does it mean so you see
water can be used in two ways you can
hurt your enemy you can hurt the
terrorist nation either by stopping the
flow of water that will hurt them
because they'll
you know
um they they need water for agriculture
and so on. So if you stop water it hurts
them but you can also hurt them by
releasing too much water which can flood
their agricultural land and you know
cause various kinds of small low low
scale damage and all that. So that's
also a way of punishing a way of hurting
the terrorist nation. There are two ways
of hurting the terrorist nation by
withholding water or giving too much
water which flows away and they can't
stop you know. Uh so the main thing we
are doing is that we are now going to be
an an unpredictable nation. Pakistan
will know have no idea as to what's
going to come next. That's what we are
doing. Uh so that's why sometimes we're
going to stop water when the Pakistanis
may need it and sometimes we'll release
a whole bunch of water as per our
convenience. That's what we will do and
we are no longer under any obligation uh
to inform Pakistan in advance as to what
we are doing. So that's why the
government must have released water
after suspending the
industry. Uh fat Bob says will India
allow an entire country that is Pakistan
to become a famine uh a country under
famine where millions of Pakistanis will
be on the brink of hunger. Does our
dharma allow
it? Does our dharma allow it?
So we have been on the receiving end of
terrorism for decades since 1979
essentially over and over and over
again. Uh tens of thousands hundreds of
thousands of Hindus were evicted from
Kashmir. God knows how many were killed.
They are still living as as as refugees
in their own country. Pakistan has been
perpetrating terrorist attacks on India.
We can't even count them. Yes. Uh so it
is is it is it dharmic to allow this to
happen to continue
forever? You know what what dharma says?
It says that a hinsa perma dharma the
the highest dharma is a
hinsa. So what does it mean? Let's dig
deeper into it. It means that hinsa is
the worst thing. Hinsa violence is the
worst thing in dharma. And we have a
nation on our border that is constantly
engaging in hinsa in
violence. It is engaging in
extraordinarily adheric activities. So
our dharma is to end a dharma to end
violence and to establish a
hinsa. And we will do it at in whatever
way we can in whatever way is needed.
When you have a bunch of
evildoers, you got to destroy them. I'm
not saying kill all Pakistanis. Many of
them may be perhaps innocent. But when
you
are a citizen of a terrorist nation, you
are a terrorist by default. See, I'll
tell you why. Let me explain. I'm sure
this is very difficult to understand
because it requires multiple levels of
thinking. Let's say you are a Pakistani
citizen. Okay? you're a Pakistani
citizen, poor person, you don't have
access to flour. Many people, you know,
they don't have access access to roti,
ata, all that stuff. They don't have
that. And and they're always facing all
kinds of problems, right? Uh but every
time a Pakistani citizen buys a
matchbox or a packet of of cigarettes or
or a small bunch of hashish or whatever
it is that they buy. Every time they buy
something there is some kind of tax on
that and that tax revenue goes to the
government which is the ISI and the
military. So every time a Pakistani
person buys anything, there is a small
tax, goods, services tax, whatever the
tax is, local added taxes, whatever it
is, every time they buy something,
purchase something in the black market,
white market, whichever market, gray
market, some portion of that money is
going to the Pakistani regime, the ISI,
army, armed forces, terrorist uh
machine, right? So simply by existing
every single Pakistani citizen is
contributing to the terrorist factory
right and most of them actually have
sympathies towards the terrorist factory
and most of them actually support it.
I'm sure some of them don't but they are
unfortunate that they are born in
Pakistan. My point is if you are a
Pakistani citizen you are wittingly or
unwittingly complicit in
terrorism and you're going to have to
pay the price for it unfortunately.
So um until we establish complete ainsa
in Pakistan until that time u
unfortunately some innocent Pakistani
citizens may have to
suffer. So the best thing for Pakistani
citizens is to leave Pakistan. That's
what I would say because now enough is
enough and uh things will no longer be
the same after after this latest
terrorist attack. Things are not going
to be the same now between India and
Pakistan. I think the clock is now
ticking for Pakistan. It's it's a
countdown. The countdown has begun. I
don't know how long the countdown will
last. It's counting down to zero. It may
last 5 years, 10 years, maybe, maybe 6
months. We'll see. But the beginning of
the end has started.
Brianka Shikhar Biswas says with
Pakistan's foreign defense minister in
Bilawaval Bhau openly acknowledging the
country's history of supporting
terrorism and several MPs making
inflammatory remarks about avenging
whatever whatever whatever while key
ministers reach out to international
media. Is Pakistan trying to craft a
strategic global message or are these
actions driven by growing internal
pressure and fear of international
isolation?
Um see what we are seeing is that the
Pakistan defense minister came on on I
don't know which channel it was a UK
channel and he said he admitted that
Pakistan has for decades been doing the
west's dirty work the dirty work of the
US the UK and the west and the dirty
work the dirty work is obviously
terrorism aimed at India and also at
Afghanistan and god knows where else
terrorism right he admitted that he
called it dirty work and then this
fellow Bilaval Bhau the son of Bayazir
Bhuto. I don't know what his position is
in the government. He seems to have some
kind of perhaps official position. I
don't keep track of these Pakistanis.
But yes, he comes on on on another UK
channel, maybe the same UK channel, TV
channel. And he also acknowledged that
Pakistan has been has had this history
of of doing dirty work or whatever it is
for the west. So it's clear that the
nation is now openly admitting their
officials are now openly admitting that
Pakistan has essentially been uh
indulging in terrorism on behalf of the
west doing the dirty work so that the
west can keep its hands clean right um
they are openly admitting it. So what
are they trying to do is the question.
Uh by admitting that you have been
indulging in terrorism, uh you can't
quite claim victimhood, right? Oh, we
have been terrorists until now, but we
also suffered from terrorism and now
that's all in the past. That's that's
the kind of statement Bilawal BH made in
his typical asinine fashion. Um that's
what he was saying. You you can't claim
victimhood if you are admitting that you
you've been indulging in terrorism for
decades. So what is Pakistan trying to
do? It's trying to lay the blame of
everything that happened on the
west. You see that's what they're doing.
That's what the the defense minister
did. That's what Bilawal BH is also
doing. Looks like there's this
orchestrated campaign, plan, whatever
you want to call it, among the Pakistani
elites to admit that
Pakistan has been a terrorist nation.
Until now they have been denying it
vehemently, but now they're admitting
it. So first firstly they admitting that
they they have done a lot of terrorism
on behalf of the west and secondly they
are pointing the finger at the west that
the west made us do it. The west is the
was the master. It was done on behalf of
the west. We were simply the proxies. So
they are pointing fingers. They're
laying the blame on the west. Now in in
what
circumstances do you
blame your
master for what you have done for for
what they made you do. That only happens
when you have given them divorce papers.
Right?
You only blame your master if you have
given them the divorce papers or if they
have given you the divorce papers. So
Pakistan is a small terrorist nation
super poor. They are in no condition to
give somebody divorce papers especially
the US. So what this implies, what this
tells you if you have some kind of
understanding is that it is the US that
has most likely served the divorce
papers to Pakistan and now Pakistan is
the jilted X and they are looking for a
new master. And now now that everything
is finished, they are blaming the West.
That's the message they're sending and
they are sending a message not to the
global audience. They're sending a
message to a prospective new master.
Now who is the new
master? Is it Russia? I don't think
Russia has too much use for
Pakistan. The nation that has use for
Pakistan is
China. That's what's going
on. Pranay Paul says with Pakistan now
officially suspending the 1972 Shimla
agreement which formed the very basis
for maintaining the line of control. Are
we witnessing the formal death of any
pretension of peace given that the
Shimla agreement was Pakistan's shield
against India taking stronger actions in
Pakistan
occup? Does this now legally and
diplomatically free India's hand to
fundamentally alter the ground
situation? How serious are the
implications of this move and could it
actually backfire massively on Pakistan
opening the door for India to reclaim
lost strategic space?
Uh once we um walked out of the of the
Indust treaty, Pakistan had to save they
had to save some
face. So the only face saving mechanism
they could find was that you know we
will no longer uh recognize the Shimla
agreement. Okay.
So that's the Shimla agreement was
something on paper and yeah it it may be
the basis for maintaining the
maintaining the line of control and
whatever else it was. So uh Pakistan had
to show its public and they had to show
the world that they have taken some kind
of retal they've done some kind of
retaliation against India. So that's why
they have suspended the Shimla agreement
and the Shimla agreement counts for
nothing. It was supposed to be have
certain clauses which the Pakistanis
have never uh respected. Right? I mean
all these decades of terrorism. Was it
respecting the Shimla agreement? So the
Shimla agreement is now
finished. Good that it's finished. It's
a relic of the past. The Indust treaty
is finished. Good that it's finished. Uh
but um now that these treaties and
everything all all of these things are
finished, they're gone. They no longer
stand. They no longer uh tenable, valid,
whatever. Does this uh legally and
diplomatically free India's hand to
fundamentally alter the ground situation
as in alter the the lines on the map? Uh
legally
[Music]
look yes I I suppose it does
diplomatically legally but you know at
the end of the day you can do it only if
you're strong enough to do it. And I
would say I think it's it's still a
little too early to start uh changing
the lines on the map. I think as of
today uh today is what date? Today is
the 3rd of May, right? Today is the 3rd
of May 2025. I think there is a
significant chance that in the next 7 to
15 days there could be some military
action taken by India against Pakistan.
I think there is a 50 to 70% chance that
in the next two weeks there will be
military action by India against
Pakistan. I think there is a chance
significant chance better than 50%
chance but even if we take military
action it will not be a massive change
of the border it will be a slap on the
face of Pakistan and some kind of
military defeat that's what will happen
it it won't be a major military
operation it will be a pulse pause war
maximum 72 wars and then unilateral uh
pause that sort of thing uh so whether
the Shimla agreement holds or not
doesn't matter. If India, if the
leadership in India decides that we need
to take certain actions, we'll take it
anyway.
Um see what will really massively
backfire in Pakistan is first of all the
rise of India as a great as a great
power as a great regional power at least
u and secondly their track record of
decades of terrorism. That's what will
massively backfire once you do such
things once you do so much terrorism
against all your enemy all all your
enemies neighbors Afghanistan India even
Iran doesn't like like Pakistan then you
know your position becomes untenable the
moment your neighbors get a chance
they're going to give it back to you
they're going to pay you back back um
with interest so uh like I said it's a
matter of time now for Pakistan it's a
matter of them what they've done in in
in the latest terrorist attack that is
the straw that broke the camel's back.
There's no going back for Pakistan now.
Mrianka Sikhar Biswas says as the US
reaffirms India's right to defend itself
in the wake of the Bahalgam terror
attack. Does this growing strategic
convergence between Washington and New
Delhi reflect a deeper shift in regional
power dynamics and how might it
influence India's posture towards
crossber terrorism and its neighbors?
Look, first of all, we don't
need any any any any certificate from
the U from the US or anybody else that
we have the right to our self-defense.
All right, first of all, we don't need
that. But yeah, very nice of the US to
say that. What does this mean? U it
means
nothing. It's possible that privately
they may be pressurizing India not to
take any action, not to take any
military action. In public they'll say
nice things or maybe in private also
they may be telling India to go ahead if
you want to. So we don't know what's
happening behind the scenes. See
diplomacy has two faces. One is the
public face, one is the private face. In
public you say nice things. In private
it's a whole different story. You can
imagine what happens in private. In
diplomacy uh it's a very different world
in private. Um so yeah the US has made
this public statements. Various US
officials have said have said said that
they stand with India. Various world
leaders from various parts of the world
have said that even the foreign minister
of Iran said that and I don't know if
the Chinese have said anything but and
so on. Uh so there's a lot of support
for India. The US has expressed support.
Uh does this mean that there's a growing
convergence between India and and the
US?
It looks like there is growing
convergence between India and the US and
there are external reasons for that. Uh
China is an issue. So
look some of you may say that China has
been doing its best to uh to engineer
some kind of uh reprosh with India. the
past year or so they have been saying
nice things and uh there has been some
kind of deescalation on the India Tibet
uh undemarcated border all of that
so yeah there's been these events the
past year or so and there have been
outreaches by China to other Indians
also in various domains uh privately
publicly wherever so the Chinese have
explored various alternatives and
options with India and and tried to see
whether you know there can be a rush and
we are obviously aminable to a rush we
don't want tensions on the border but
it's true that uh the kilash manser over
yatra is starting now it's it's almost
about to start apparently and and lots
of confidence building measures are
going on but the fact is that there are
still tensions on the India Tibet border
there is still kind of a standoff
situation
to some extent, not as much as in 2020
for sure, but you know, satellite
imagery tells you that the Chinese are
are building more and more
infrastructure on their side of of the
India Tibet border. So, they are
actually strengthening their their
infrastructure and their military
presence and posture on the border. So,
it's kind of, you know, saying one
thing, doing the other. Um so that what
does it tell us? It tells us that we
have to be
forever vigilant when it comes to China
and as long as China holds debate it's
going to be a constant problem for us
especially as long as China is three
four times more powerful than us as it
is today. So when you have that
situation it is natural that you will
seek external
uh friends. Let's say there are no
friends in geopolitics but let's let's
call the term friends. So which external
friends can we look at or partners can
we look at the natural partner
historically has been Russia but Russia
is in a peculiar situation right now
where it is is very very heavily
dependent on China. So Russia and and
even if it were not dependent on China,
it Russia was never going to be in a
position to come to India in India
support if there's a India China
war. So Russia is out of the question.
So who else is left? There's no other
bigger power left except for the US. And
the US has a very very very strong
interest in the region especially the
fact that they want to stop China's rise
and and you know they want to contain
China. So it makes sense for us to work
with them. Now we don't want to contain
China. We don't have anything against
China's rise. We just don't want to be
in a position where where China can you
know attacks militarily. So we have to
be careful. We as an India not to become
pawns, not to become a big pawn on a
geopolitical board. We need to have our
own autonomy, our own strategic autonomy
and we're going to ensure that happens.
But we're going to work with the US to
whatever extent is possible wherever we
have convergence of interests. So that's
what's
happening. Um and the US also needs
India in a variety of ways. They are
decoupling from China very rapidly. uh
their trade with China has has gone out
gone down to nearly zero more or less
and uh they need another place where
they can have things manufactured. So
the only nation that can replace
something of the size of China is
something of the size of India. So India
is increasingly important and so it
makes sense for them for the US
uh to support India in various ways. So
there is this growing increasing
strategic convergence between Washington
and New Delhi and it does reflect this
deeper shifting of international global
power dynamics not regional but global
power
dynamics and how might this influence
India's posture towards crossber
terrorism and its neighbors look we have
no issue with any neighbor as long as
they leave us alone we leave them alone
and we want to be friends with everybody
and when it comes to certain neighbors
we have most I mean historically we have
had some issues but you know when it
comes to neighbors like Sri Lanka when
it comes to neighbors like Nepal we have
essentially no issues it's only
neighbors like Pakistan and increasingly
east Pakistan of late and Maldives at
times that we've had issues
um so as long as the neighbors don't
create any trouble we we have always
left them alone right
um more or less more or less there have
been issues in the past at at times when
certain Indian governments have taken
very stupid um very very
counterproductive actions but okay we'll
not discuss that here because it's not
relevant so our posture towards crossber
terrorism is going to get harder and
harder now we're going to be less
tolerant of crossber terrorism
u if if another big incident happens now
like what happened in pahelam I I can
assure you it's the end of end of the
world of Pakistan So we are going to be
extremely intolerant now of crossber
terrorism and it's high time uh we adopt
that
posture. Okay. Manka Shakhar Biswis
says, "Does the deportation of a
significant number of Pakistani women
residing in India, some even married to
Indian security personnel highlight a
growing national security concern or is
it a reflection of deeper systemic
vulnerabilities in border and identity
identity verification
protocols and Prrenipal says with
Gujarat police bravely detaining over
1,000 illegal Bangladeshies, Pakistanis,
Rohingyas, many of whom had created
fraudulent documents through whatever
place. How serious is the internal
security threat posed by this scale of
infiltration? While the Gujarat police's
work is commendable, isn't it clear that
these numbers are still just the tip of
the iceberg and far from enough to fully
clean out the threat? From a national
security perspective, how urgently must
India act not just against the
infiltrators but also against the
political and logistical networks
enabling this demographic and security
assault. Yes. So um after the Bahelgam
terrorist attack by Pakistan, India
revoked all the visas given to
Pakistanis and said that they have 48
hours to leave the country. And for
those who had come across the Atari or
whatever or which whichever uh border
point they were given a week or so to
leave from the same place and then there
was some kind of a crackdown within
certain parts of India on Pakistanis who
had been overstaying their visas
illegally and thousands of them were
discovered and rounded up and in Gujarat
apparently more than a thousand illegal
uh infiltrators. Bangladesh is Pakistani
Pakistanis Ringas were rounded up
detained or whatever. The question
is you
know when the government issues the
order to round up the illegals the
authorities are able to find them so
quickly right incredibly fast as if they
know exactly where they are. So if if
it's known where these people are
staying and they're
illegals, why have they been allowed to
stay in India of so
long? There are millions of illegal
Bangladeshi infiltrators all across
India. It's it's it's an open secret. In
2014, the number official number given
by the government was 50 million in
2014. Today it must be 100 million
possibly. I'm speculating possibly.
Why is no action being being taken
against these illegal infilters? Why are
they not being
deported? It looks like the government
authorities know where these people are
and who are illegals. They know
it. And when such a terrorist attack
happens, they will push out a few
thousand Pakistanis. How come these
Pakistanis were living in India all
these years? Some of them were living
since 1965.
They have discovered like 80,000
Pakistani women married to Indians and
living in India but still holding
Pakistani
passports. They have discovered
Pakistani infiltrators who served in the
Jammu and Kashmir police
allegedly and who had been living for
decades. Is
India a sovereign nation or is India a
joke of a
nation? And okay, the Gujarat police has
detained let's say a thousand of these
illegal infiltrators. They detained
them. Have they been deported or were
they rounded up? And then what happens
with
them? It came in the news that these
people have been rounded up. Okay. Were
they expelled out of the
country? What happened after they were
rounded up is my
question. And apart from Gujarat, I can
assure
you there are millions of these illegals
all across the country. Why have other
states not taken any
action? I think the the question of
illegal infiltration is not a state
subject. I think the central government
has to take the lead in this. So I think
it's it's it's what we have seen is
merely the tip of the
iceberg. It is a gigantic national
security threat. Imagine the Indian
taxpayer paying for a 100 million
illegal infiltrators who hate the
country.
who are serving in the uh in in in
allegedly in police forces and god knows
where else. Some of them said on camera
that they've been voting they have cast
their vote in India. How does a
Pakistani get to vote in
India? It's high time the government
takes this very seriously and cleans the
nation out from inside.
I mean it's it's it's
mindboggling the the level of
dysfunction the Indian government has
that we are so deeply penetrated by
penetrated by people who hate
us by our
enemies who are enjoying the privilege
of living in India while working against
the country. It's incredible incredible
I I just don't know what to say. I have
no words to express how outraged I am
and I hope you all are also
outraged
incredible and and what's the question
uh that was asked is it a reflection of
deeper systematic systemic
vulnerabilities in border and
identification protocols I mean who
issues these fake ID
cards these ID cards Aadhaar cards and
PAN cards and whatn not these are
governmentisssued ID
IDs who is issuing
them. If a Pakistani person gets a voter
license, voter voter ID card, it means
some government officials gave him the
voter ID card and it was issued by
government
officials. There is a serious problem in
India. Serious serious problem. It's not
just the infiltrators who are a problem.
There's an entire Yeah, like Prrenai
Prren Paul says, political and
logistical networks enabling
this. Um I mean the central government
has to take some action and it's high
time they take that action on
priority now that we are cracking down
on on Pakistan. It's a time to crack
down on the Pakistanis and Bangladeshes
and Rohingyas and cookies and whoever
else are illegally squatting on Indian
territory. All these illegal invaders
and infiltrators, evict them all. Deport
all
illegals. Enough of
this. Okay. Manushi Sha says,
"Cancelling of Pakistani visas brought
into light so many crossber marriages of
Indians married there, having kids there
and coming and residing in India. What
should be done with them?"
Sunmoon0877 says, "How come the
government just sent off illegal
immigrants who lived here for almost two
decades and the worst part is that they
cast their votes in India? Why did the
government send them back without any
punishment? Will they send off any
Pakistanis and not Bangladeshes, not
Rohingyas also?" Yeah, that's good
questions. Okay, let's say Yeah. So
first of all I don't know how many
80,000 crossber marriages Pakistani
women married to Indians here and living
here having kids here but holding
Pakistani passports and Indian women
marrying in Pakistan but bringing their
kids here. I don't know what kind of an
absolute
mess this situation
is. It looks like we have no border at
all. Freeforall. Come do whatever you
want. It looks like that. And uh what
Sunmoon is asking is these illegal
immigrants were sent back. They were not
punished. You know who should be
punished? The government officials who
allowed this to happen, who knew who
knew this was happening and who were
facilitating all of this, they should be
punished. It's not the Pakistanis fault
that they were allowed to live here.
It's our job, it's our government's job
to do their due diligence and ensure
that there are no foreign illegal
infiltrators living in India.
Um and yeah the the other question is
will they only send the Pakistanis back?
What about the Bangladeshes? What about
the Rohhingas? What about the other uh
infiltrators in India? There's a huge
problem in in Manipur, the cookies. God
knows how many lakhs of them are are are
squatting on Manipur territory. What
about these illegals? Is India a dham
shala? Like they say anybody can just
come in and do whatever they want. I I I
don't know. So these are the questions
that the government needs to answer.
Um people obviously will be outraged
that that all of this has come to
light. They're not outraged it has come
to light. It's good. It's a good thing
it's come to light. But will any action
be taken now or will we wait another 20
10 20 years until the problem gets even
more deeprooted? So I think the
government should act. It's high time
the government acts and you need to tell
the people, show the people that you
you're acting. Don't just do it in
secret. Show the citizenry that you are
rectifying the pro situation and solving
the problem. Please do that.
Samartha says given the recent statement
by Muhammad Yus' Yunus's aid that if
India strikes Pakistan, Bangladesh
should align with China to severe
India's northeast from the rest of the
country. What does this provocative
assertion reveal especially as regional
tensions reach a critical point? Could
it signal the beginning of a coordinated
geopolitical strategy aimed at
encircling India? And does it s suggest
that China's string of pearl strategy is
evolving into a more assertive and
potentially successful containment
framework? Look,
um the Muhammad Yunus
regime came to power in Bangladesh and
Bangladesh became East Pakistan as a
consequence of of a coup deta that was
engineered by the Biden regime, the Joe
Biden regime. Okay, she hassa the
democratically elected leader of
Bangladesh was ousted in a military
coup and this puppet regime came to
power and Muhammad Yunus is the puppet
that is the face of the regime but the
nation is actually ruled by the army. It
was not a student re revolution. Those
students are being are being oppressed
today. Not a single student is in the
government. It's a joke if you still
believe it was a student revolution. So
it was a coup da it was a color
revolution
uh engineered by the US by the by the
Biden
administration and uh Muhammadus
has ancient ties with the Democrats and
the Sorosh ecosystem and all that okay
it's well
known so
um and and at the same time a couple of
years before that there was a kuda in
Pakistan as well and Iran Khan was
ousted and whoever came to power after
Iran Khan was put in power by the
Americans. So there were two regime
change operations that happened East
Pakistan and West Pakistan. First in
West Pakistan, then in East Pakistan,
both done by the Biden regime. Now
there's a new regime in the US, the
Trump regime. And they seem to have no
interest in continuing the freebies
given to uh these vasal states. So
that's why the Pakistanis are very
openly looking for a new master in China
which and China will be happy to oblige.
So that's done and clearly Muhammad
Yunus is also fishing for a new master.
He was recently in Beijing where he made
these statements in English from Chinese
territory that we can cut off India's
far east northeast and it's a landlocked
place and China should invest in
Bangladesh because we can cut off
India's northeast that sort of thing. He
made these statements openly at the age
of what 97 or whatever he is. He's still
not mature enough not to make these
statements in public.
Uh so clearly uh he would have been
encouraged by his Chinese hosts and
he maybe it was deliberate, maybe it was
a slip of the tongue, but I'm glad it
came out.
So So it looks like we have two vasals
which used to be American vasals which
will now be Chinese.
Um and what this tells you is that uh
the Muhammad Yunus regime is is uh very
deeply
anti-India and if they get a chance
they'll be very happy to to unleash
trouble in India's far east. Anyway, we
already have enough trouble in the far
east because of project K cookie land
for Christ which was another uh pet
project of the Biden regime and then the
deeper deep state in the US.
Uh so what does this mean? It means that
the Chinese may get involved in in
Bangladesh now. And u look the string of
pearl strategy was something from the
1990s and 2000s and obviously it evolves
and the Chinese would obviously love to
to encircle India to to contain India.
But it it won't be that easy. It won't
be that easy because India is not some
not no longer a nation that just takes
things uh passively. India is proactive
proactively uh you know shaping its own
neighborhood itself. So it's going to be
a tug-of-war kind of situation. But it
looks like the Chinese are now going to
be involved in East as well as West
Pakistan and Muhammad Inus and his
regime they are very strongly
anti-India. By now it should be um
evident to
everybody. Right. Brianka Shikhar Bispas
says if Pakistan were to launch nuclear
missiles in a desperate
escalation would India's advanced air
defense systems like the Pitri air
defense the advanced air defense the
S400 etc be capable of intercepting and
neutralizing those threats midair or
would such a situation expose critical
gaps in overall nuclear deterrence
stability of nations around across the
with similar defense systems. Look, let
me tell you something. The North Koreans
have pretty capable uh ballistic
missiles. They have ballistic missiles
that can reach essentially any part of
the US from North Korea. And I can
assure you that apart from a few
American cities, most of the cities are
setting targets, setting ducks. If they
were to hit Hawaii, there's nothing the
Americans can do to stop the missile
from hitting Hawaii. Um, if they they
were to try and hit, let's say, some
interior part of the
US, they'll be successful. The Americans
will probably be able to successfully
defend places like Washington DC, uh,
New York City, the major cities, they'll
defend, they'll be able to defend them
because they have adequate defenses,
anti-bballistic missile defenses there.
But the US is is a continent-sized
nation and most of it is not going to be
defensible. That's what you have to
understand because antibbalistic missile
defense systems are essentially point
defense systems or small region defense
systems. For example, let's take the
example of the Israeli Iron Dome. The
Iron Dome system can defend a small
territory roughly the size of Israel.
And even that's not
infallible. It's simply a mathematical
thing. You know, if you want to breach
the defenses, let's say the Iron Dome
system can can has X number of missiles,
anti-missile missiles that they can
launch. All you have to do is launch one
more than X and that's it. You you you
penetrated it. Sometimes you may have
these uh laser systems. So you can take
out incoming missiles by laser that may
be more resilient and so on. But even
that is point defense. You're simply
able to defend a small area, a city
perhaps like Tel
Aviv. You can't defend the whole of
Israel with a laser system. Unless you
have hundreds of laser systems all over
the place, you can't. So with that
understood, if Pakistan were to launch
ballistic missiles, forget about
nuclear, let's say
missiles, then what can India do? India
will be able to defend certain cities
where you where
these anti-missile systems are placed.
Uh I will not name the cities but
certain very large cities, major cities
will have these defense systems already
installed. So the pritu air defense
system it's it's a it's a two two-stage
defense system. There's an exo
atmospheric endo atmospheric. One
interception is done at 40 km altitude.
Another is done at 60 km altitude. And
we also have an exo atmospheric
interceptor which is the ASAP system
which can also probably take out
ballistic missiles uh if it's traveling
at like 10 kilometers a second or
something that sort of thing. So we have
multiple layers of of defenses but these
defenses don't um cover the whole of
India. They can only cover some small
areas unless you have hundreds of
defense systems all across India which
would be prohibitively expensive. No
country can afford that. So it's only
strategic targets that will be defended
major cities nuclear installations and
so on so forth. You get the point. Um,
so that's that's that's the situation
and I'm not sure how advanced our
antibbalistic missile defense uh systems
are. We have been testing them and
developing them since the 2000s. I'm
sure they're in pretty advanced stages
of development and pretty advanced
capabilities, I'm sure. Um, and we also
have the S400 system, which is not
primarily an antibbalistic missile
defense system. It's a defense system
that that is designed to take out
incoming aircraft and possibly cruise
missiles and perhaps ballistic missiles
of a certain of a certain quality or
maybe short to medium-range ballistic
missiles perhaps. It it
depends and even the Pritaria defense
and all will be able to take out
ballistic missiles of certain classes.
Uh and the actual capabilities of these
defense systems are obviously uh
classified. They are not known to the
public. And that's how it's supposed to
be. So the point is any anti-bballistic
missile defense system is at best a
something that can defend a small area
against ballistic missile attack. It
can't defend the defend the whole of the
country. We have a subcontinent sized
nation. You can't defend the whole of
it. That's just the
deal.
Right. Okay. Next question is by Mr. 88.
The government of India has announced
that they will do a cast census in the
next population census. Reservation in
the private sector is almost inevitable
now. No political party respects the
meritocracy and after the cast sensus it
is obvious that they will use the data
for their own political gain. What
future is this nation actually aspiring
for for its citizens? Is it even ideal
for a responsible taxpayer of this
nation to stay in this apathine state?
Okay. So there's been this announcement
by some I don't know which minister that
uh whenever the next census happens uh
they're going to include cast in that.
So they're going to collect cast data
information uh in the next census. I
mean the the census was supposed to
happen I think in 2021 but because of
the corona virus uh pandemic the
lockdowns and all that it could not
happen. I'm not sure when the next
census is going to happen. But whenever
it happens, they're going to include uh
cast. They're going to collect cast data
and statistics. That's what has been
stated. That's the announcement that was
made. Uh what's my reaction? My reaction
is I'm going to wait and watch. I don't
know what it means. I'm not going to go
out there and give you a knee-jerk
reaction. Oh, this is terrible. Blah
blah blah. Or oh, it's great great. I
have no idea. What does it mean? First
of all, what is cast? Is it like those
four classical casts that the British
had entrenched in India or is it the
vernas and jatis in which you have
hundreds of casts? What exactly is it?
Um that I don't think it's clear at this
point. And
look one
thing I'm sure you understand is a fact
of life. CAST is required in all
government documents right in your birth
certificate in a school living
certificate whatever certificate cast is
there. So if cast has already been uh
you know standardized and and mandated
by the government then maybe they want
to understand the statistics of the
nation's uh castbased distribution. I'm
not sure if it's a good thing or a bad
thing or what but um does it mean that
reservation in private sector is almost
inevitable? I am not sure of that. Um I
obviously am not in favor of any kind of
reservations except for non-castbased
reservations which are economic status
based reservations. You know it's okay
in my opinion to to to give assistance
to people who are financially genuinely
backward. So reservations should be
given on the basis of your financial
status economic status whether you'll be
below poverty line or not on the basis
of cast. But this is now entrenched in
the system and any political party that
undo that will is guaranteed to lose the
next election because Indians love
freebies right we are a nation of
freeloaders.
Um so cast is whether we like it or not
it's it's a part of the system. So maybe
the government wants to actually you
know collect data and statistics about
who contributes what to the uh excheer
or tax whatever. I have no idea. So, I'm
going to reserve my judgment until more
information comes out. I'm not sure if
it's a good thing or a bad thing. I have
said this multiple times on the record
that I am not in favor of reservations
unless they are economic status based
reservations, not cast based
reservations and I I have said this
multiple times that I am I don't believe
in in this cast thing. We should abolish
cast. We should abolish cast entirely.
But look, there is an idealistic utopian
worldview. The government lives in the
real world. People like me can give all
these all these all these
recommendations and suggestions because
uh we don't have to implement them. The
government it it will face the
consequences of any action they take
good or bad. And obviously if you're in
politics, you want to be in power. You
don't want to lose elections. So it's
the nature of the system that the
government will do whatever the pe
whatever the majority of the people
want. Uh so that's the world. That's the
real world, isn't it? So uh so it looks
like there's going to be um cast
included in the next census. It's not a
cast census. It's a population census
which will include various parameters.
One of those parameters is going to be
cast. So until more details emerge and
are brought out. I will reserve my
judgment and I'm not going to make any
any
um I'm not going to pass any judgment at
this point in time. Let's wait and watch
until more information comes out. I'm
not sure if it's a good thing or a bad
thing. Maybe it's a good thing in some
way. Let's wait and watch. Let's be a
little patient. Let more information
come out. Um there is no guarantee that
uh because cast is not going to be
included in the census. That means that
uh the private sector um is going to you
know reservations are going to be
brought into the private sector. I'm not
sure about that and I hope it doesn't
happen. I am not in favor of that and if
it if if reservation if reservations are
brought into the private sector also
um that that look it's not happened so I
I'm not saying anything if it
happens yeah well that won't be a very
nice
thing Paul says with the US now signing
a mineral and reconstruction deal with
Ukraine giving UK giving it preferential
access to Ukraine's natural resources.
Are we witnessing the return of
investment ROI phase of the West's
involvement in the war? Is this about
rebuilding Ukraine or securing long-term
strategic control over its resources
under the guise of aid? And how should
other resourcerich but vulnerable
nations interpret this model of support
turning into economic
capture? So, the US and Ukraine have
finally signed that minerals deal. That
deal was supposed to be signed the day
Zalinski visited Washington. Uh but
Zalinsky had other ideas and there was a
public
fight on live TV that Zalinski uh
undertook uh against Trump and and Vance
and whoever else and the deal was not
signed at at that point in time. And now
finally after some water has flown
flowed under the bridge the deal was
signed I believe uh yesterday or day
before ju just in the past 14 hours
something like that and um it's a
revised deal it's not the same deal that
was supposed to be signed when Zalinski
was in Washington it's a revised deal
the Ukrainians have pushed back against
the Americans and they have extracted
some concessions from the Americans so
let's see in in case you want to See let
let me put that on the screen and let's
quickly take a look at what this deal is
like you know roughly roughly let's take
a look roughly at what this deal is like
let me remove this from the screen so
the US and Ukraine this is from CNN the
US and Ukraine signed critical minerals
deal after months of tense negotiations
and this came out on the 1st of May
today is the 3rd of May so past 48 hours
yes uh so the US and Ukraine have signed
an economic partnership agreement that
will give Washington access to Kiev's
mineral resources in exchange exchange
for establishment uh establishing an
investment fund in Ukraine. The US and
Ukraine have been okay. They've been
trying to hammer it out. Compared to
earlier drafts, the final agreement is
reportedly less lopsided in favor of the
US and is not as farreaching. It
stipulates that future American military
assistance to Ukraine will count as part
of the US investment into the fund
rather than calling it calling for
reimbursement for past
assistance.
Um okay, that's good. uh all
that uh what else? What else? A among
the terms of the agreement are full
ownership and control of the resources
staying with Ukraine. So the UK so
Ukraine retains full ownership and
control of the re of the resources. It
doesn't uh automatically start belonging
to Washington. All resources on our
territory and in territorial waters
belong to Ukraine. It is the Ukrainian
state that determines what and where to
extract subs soil remains under
Ukrainian ownership that's established
in the
agreement. Um
um the details of the agreement have not
been made public. Ukraine's prime
minister said that we will not the deal
will not include assistance provided
before its signing which means that
whatever money and arms all that the
Americans paid sent to the Ukraine that
is not to be considered as a debt that
Ukraine has to repay to the US uh and so
on. So yeah it's it's a much better deal
than before and it doesn't give
Washington complete ownership of half of
Ukraine. Zelinskate complained that the
previous deal was essentially signing
away ownership of Ukraine to the US and
this seems to be different. So the
Ukrainians seem to have been tough
negotiators and they seem to have done a
good deal of renegotiating and reframing
the deal. But uh the US administration
will portray this as a big win for the
US to its public. uh Trump will say that
you know we got what what we we were
asking for and u we spent all this money
in the Ukraine war and we are now going
to u get this ROI on that. Uh so it's
it's it's going to be spun in a variety
of ways from whichever way you're
looking at it. So there's going to be
some ROI definitely.
uh but u all the money let's say about
$500 billion worth of money of of
resources that the US spent during the
Ukraine war in assisting Ukraine that is
not going to count as a debt that
Ukraine has to pay the west has to pay
the US so that's that's a big change
from the previous deal
um so it's not really about rebuilding
Ukraine it's about exploiting Ukrainian
resources as much as possible that's
obviously what it is and any
resourcerich or vulnerable country has
to be very careful that it doesn't get
used in this manner the way Ukraine has
been used.
Um this this war the Ukraine war has
been a proxy war. It's been a war that
NATO fought against Russia using Ukraine
as the proxy. And who has come out as
the loser in the deal? Obviously
Ukraine. they've lost I don't know how
many people and you know they've lost so
much territory and they seem to have
lost some amount of sovereignty as well.
So there you have
it. Okay, next questions. Mrianka Sikhar
Biswas says as India moves forward with
the Rafal deal's next phase seeking not
just fighter jets but a meaningful
transfer of technology does this signal
a strategic shift towards defense
self-reliance or is it a calculated move
to recalibrate global power dynamics in
the Indo-Pacific region and Jagdish Mali
says some foreign affairs experts are
saying that France has agreed to give a
transfer of technology along with the
Rafal jets in the 4.1 one for in the
$7.4 billion deal. Is this true? Will
France give 100% technology transfer
along with the Rafal jets to India? So
the deal seems to be worth about $7.4
billion. Uh how many Rafal jets are we
getting? 26. Let's do some
math. We're getting 26 Rafal jets.
Let's say if one Rafal jet were to cost
$10 million, then the deal would be $260
million. So clearly this is much more.
So let's say a Rafal jet costs
hypothetically $100 million. Then the
deal would be $2.6
billion. But this is more than that. So
it looks like if we just divide the the
the amount which is $7.4 4 billion by by
the number of fighter planes 26 that
we're getting then it it amounts to from
that naive perspective it amounts to it
means that each Rafal jet naively would
cost about 285 or so million dollars
which would make it the most expensive
fighter jet in human history. I mean the
most expensive fighter plane today is
the F-35 which costs about $110 million
a piece for the export variant and this
from this deal it it looks like the
Rafal jet naively would cost about $285
million a piece which obviously doesn't
make sense. So obviously there is
something else the deal beyond the Rafal
jets. There is some kind of so there is
some kind of transfer of technology.
There are spare parts. There are
defense. There are there are missile
systems. There are all kinds of other
things attached to the Rafale fighter
planes that are part of the deal. It's
not just the fighter planes we're
getting. We're getting a whole lot of
other stuff um including some form of
transfer of technology. Now what exactly
is the specifics of the transfer of
technology aspect of the deal? I'm not
sure. I've not looked into it. But there
is some kind of transfer of technology.
Uh are we going to get the full transfer
of technology of the entire Rafal so
that we can we can manufacture the whole
of the thing here itself in India? I'm
not quite sure that that's the case.
There's going to be some kind of
transfer of technology. The French
obviously are going to not give all of
the technology away. U unless we agree
to manufacture 100 or 200 Rafals in
India then they may be willing to give
the whole technology but we are buying
26 uh the naval Rafal jets for the next
aircraft carrier or whichever aircraft
carrier. Um so I don't know which
foreign affair expert is saying what uh
transfer of technology yes there is a
transfer of technology component in the
deal. There are other components like
weapons, packages and and other stuff as
well which is which is the reason why
the the total amount of the deal is $7.4
billion which is not just the price of
the jets of the fighter planes but a
whole lot of other stuff as well
including transfer of technology.
Um so yes we are we have the strategic
partnership with the French uh and there
is some transfer of technology. Uh does
this mean a strategic shift towards
self-reliance? We are trying to be as
self-reliant as possible. We have been
shifting towards self-reliance ever
since Mr. Modi came to power Amanda Bha
in defense and whatnot. And we are now
actually exporting some weapon systems
which we never did in the past. So we
are moving towards self-reliance. It's a
long process. It's not going to happen
overnight. Um, it's not a calculated
move to recalibrate global power
dynamics in the Indopacific region. Not
that sort of thing. It is a calculated
move to become progressively more and
more self-reliant in terms of
technology, especially defense
technology. That's what we're doing. Uh,
will France give 100% technology
transfer along with the Rafal jets to
India? I doubt it very much. they will
not give a 100% technology transfer
unless we agree I would say to build 100
or 200 200 of these fighter planes in
India in that case they will move they
will be probably willing in that case to
move the entire manufacturing ecosystem
into India so for that we would have to
manufact we would have to sign a deal
for maybe 100 or maybe more Rafal jets
in that case it may happen for 26 I
don't think they will transfer the
technology fully there'll be some
technology transfer maybe a good amount
of technology transfer but not entire
technology transfer. That's the way I
see
it. Sam uh says with the US granting
full technology transfer for the Shakti
semiconductor FAB developed by Indian
firms Bhat Semi and third tech in
collaboration with the US space force.
Does this significant procurement
suggest that India is increasingly
aligning with Washington's strategic
interests? Particularly in light of the
doctrine you mentioned where Donald
Trump may have privately stated, "You're
either with us or against us." India
appears to be to have unequivocally
chosen the position of we are with you
in the US. Could this be seen as a clear
indicator of India's strategic shift
towards the US especially given that the
US may view India as a crucial partner
in countering China in the US does view
excuse me the US does view India as a
critical partner in countering China
China there's no question about it right
India is is the only nation in in in
Asia that is capable of countering China
and that's why it's it's going to be
very much part it's going to be front
and center in the US strategy to contain
China. So that is clear. Now I did say
that Trump will probably privately tell
us that is privately tell our leadership
that you are either with us or against
us when it comes to China and other
things. I did say that and it's possible
that Mr. Trump may have uh said that
privately. But when it comes to the
Shakti semiconductor fab
um the news that the US uh had given
this full technology transfer uh to this
fab this news came out in se I think in
September last year
2024 that's before Trump came to power
so that happened during the Biden regime
the Biden uh
administration so there So you can see
that even before Trump came to power
there was this this growing strategic
convergence between India and the US and
it's going to only accelerate uh during
the Trump
presidency.
Um so yes this significant procurement
does suggest that India is increasingly
aligning with Washington strategic
interests or maybe vice versa. Maybe
Washington is increasingly aligning
aligning with India strategic interest
or maybe both are going strategically in
the same uh direction where their
interests converge and align. So uh
there are signs and indications that
India is is demonstrating some kind of
strategic shift towards the US. Uh but
it's not going to be a
complete complete uh alignment with the
US or becoming an ally of the US. India
will remain autonomous. India will
remain sovereign. India will have its
own interests and uh
everything um that we do with the US is
going to be negotiated probably on a
case by case basis. But it's it's
obviously very evident the US sees India
as a crucial partner in countering China
and the Chinese only have themselves to
blame for that.
Okay, Kumar says, "With Iran's uranium
enrichment now approaching we weapons
grade weapons grade levels in recent US
diplomatic overtures stalling, what are
the most likely scenarios for the 2025
US Iran negotiations and which key
indicators we should we monitor to
anticipate each outcome?" It's a good
question. For that, I'm going to have to
go to my Twitter account. I'm going to
just put put a tweet on the screen that
I had tweeted some some time ago about
this very matter. Uh let me give just
give me a second. I'll put that on the
screen very
rapidly. Okay, let's bring this on the
screen. That's my tweet from from a
while ago and that essentially
essentially answers your question.
So, so this is a tweet of mine from
what's the date? Uh, April 19, 2025. So,
that's about a couple of weeks ago. I
put it out and I said that there's a
high possibility of a stalemate. The US
has adopted a maximalist stance. The US
insists that Iran fully dismantle its
nuclear program and all of its
enrichment facilities. You cannot enrich
Iran uranium. That's what the US says.
And Iran obviously refuses to budge on
its red lines. Iran says that its
enrichment rights are
non-negotiable. So the most likely
outcome I said on April 19 is that there
will be no agreement. There will be a
prolonged impass assuming that neither
side is willing to make any major
concessions. Obviously neither side will
make major concessions. Impact no
sanctions relief for Iran. And the less
likely outcome is that there there can
be an interim deal or some kind of
deescalatory understanding only if
cooler heads and creative diplomacy
prevail
which have not prevailed. So that's the
deal. So I had laid it out on April 19
what was going to most likely happen and
that's exactly where we are today. Two
weeks from that time from the day I
tweeted that. Um so there's a stalemate,
there is an impass. Uh recently, I think
today or yesterday or whenever it was,
the news came out that the Iranians have
cancelled or postponed the next round of
negotiations which were supposed to
happen whenever. So they have canceled
that or postponed that. So looks like
you know progress is not happening and
the Americans like I said have adopted a
maximalist stance. Iran has to abandon
its nuclear program. Iran has to give up
its attempts to enrich uranium and so
on. And obviously no sovereign nation
will accept such terms.
Um so look I don't know what uh uranium
Iran's uranium enrichment
u uh capabilities are right now whether
it's 60% like is being said by some
people or whether it is closing on on
closing in on 90% 95% which is weapons
grade uranium I'm not sure what the
capabilities are what what the status is
but they have been at it for a very long
time the Iranians and I well if you were
to ask me if you are if were to ask me
to give you my best guess, my best
estimate, I would say they have enough
uranium enriched uranium for a few
nuclear warheads at least for a few
maybe maybe five let's say tactical
nuclear warheads kiloton scale warheads
that's that's that would be my best uh
estimate or
guess um so yeah that's where we are and
it looks like there's going to be no
progress on that look what the Americans
were trying to
do and are trying to do.
Um, see, ever since Trump came to power,
they've been trying to isolate China.
Uh, Trump wanted to end the Ukraine war
on day one. So, he and Putin, he
thought, would sit down and decide on
what happens to Ukraine and sign an
agreement and the war is over. But the
world has a way of being
inconvenient. So, that did not happen.
The European nations came in the way.
the western European nations, EU and
NATO nations came in the way and goed
Zalinsky not to give in and then
Zalinsky went to Washington and fought
in the vice white house with Trump and
uh and Vance and things did not progress
and for some time Trump stopped giving
aid to Ukraine. Now it started again now
the the minerals deal is is signed. So
what Trump initially wanted was to bring
Putin on his side by giving him a good
good uh deal to to end the the Ukraine
war. That did not happen. And and after
the the Europeans came in the way and
and u Zelinsky dragged his feet and all
this happens all this happened then
Putin started adopting a maximal a
maximalist stance. he became very rigid
on his demands
um with his demands and as a consequence
now the Americans have pulled out of uh
whatever mediation they were doing. So
looks like the Ukraine war is not
ending. Trump had said he had promised
that I will end the day the war on day
one. It's not happened. He has failed in
that. Uh so what he wanted to do put
what Trump wanted to do was to bring
Putin on his side and by bringing Putin
on his side he wanted to isolate
Xiinping and
Beijing. That was number one. Then he
wanted to slam slam all those tariffs on
China the 145% tariffs and all that
which he has done. That has completely
decoupled the two economies. there's no
more trade now essentially al it's gone
down to practically zero. So um so that
would um put a huge amount of pressure
on
China and then probably he wanted to
give some kind of deal to
Iran to bring Iran also on his side if
possible he tried uh but by adopting a
maximalist stance he ensured that Iran
doesn't come on his side. Uh so what's
happened is that there is this tug of
war going on right now in the world
between the US and China. The US wants
to bring as many nations as possible on
their side. The tried with Russia did
not
work because Russia also is not stupid.
Putin is not stupid. He understands that
long-term I mean short term you may get
something longterm that's a whole
different story. Iran also understands
that. So uh the bottom line is that
Russia and Iran and China and North
Korea are the nucleus of a new
coalition. Maybe some other nations may
join them. Uh Mr. Xiinping was recently
in the last couple of weeks on a world
wind world wind tour of Southeast Asia,
Vietnam and which other which are other
countries he visited. And um apparently
it was a very good trip and these
nations are eager for Chinese
investments but they are wary of Chinese
expansion and so on. So it's same old
story. So what we are seeing is a
decoupling of the world and Iran is is
something the Americans tried to bring
on the side. It's probably not going to
work. So this this deal is is
essentially a non-starter. The Americans
walked away from the last deal they had.
Trump walked away unilaterally from the
last nuclear deal with Iran. The
Iranians are not going to be that easy
to convince this time. And obviously
with a maximalist approach doesn't work.
If you are uh you know pointing a gun at
somebody and then saying let's let's
let's negotiate doesn't work. So yeah
that's the way it's going to
go. Okay 44 Krishnan says why are
American missionaries hellbent on
converting East Asia as seen in Korea,
Nepal and parts of China? Are the chi
Chinese and Japanese aware of this? Why
are these two cultural Asian powers not
taking any covert actions?
Um yes uh if you go to South Korea you
will see that South Korea is now
probably a Christian majority country.
Buddhism is very much on the decline
now. It's kind of more and more becoming
a fringe religion in a nation that was
Buddhist for more more than 1500 years
probably almost 2,000 years. So the
American missionaries have wiped out
Buddhism from from Korea, South Korea.
And it's more and more Christian nation,
South Korea. And this what made this
possible? It's the US occupation of
South Korea that made it possible. South
Korea is under US
occupation. Most of you will will be
astonished to hear that South Korea is
under permanent US military occupation.
It's been that way since the 1950s,
since the end of the Korean War
um since the end of the hostilities of
the Korean War. The war has technically
never ended. So the the nation is under
US military occupation and where the US
military is there, you'll have US
missionaries running riot and that's why
they have been able to convert so many
Koreans. When it comes to Japan,
um there are lots of Japanese who have
become atheists kind of but uh
Christianity has not made s so much so
so big of an of of an inroad in Japan as
compared to South Korea. The Japanese
are more resilient despite also being
under US military
occupation. Uh the Japanese have been
under US military occupation since 1945
and they have been under very heavy US
military occupation. The US has more
than 120 130 permanent US permanent
military bases on Japanese territory. Uh
but the Japanese have not been that easy
to convert. Many Japanese probably
identify as atheists but Japanese mo but
many Japanese still practice their their
culture Shinto Buddhism a mixture of
both and that's how it is. China there
seems to be a lot of Christians there
also but the the but the but the Chinese
government is very very strict about
this and they they appoint their own uh
bishops the the Vatican doesn't get to
decide who who becomes a bishop and who
becomes a cardinal and whatn not I think
it's the Chinese government that decides
it and uh so they they have maintained
some sort of control over the uh over
the over the presence of Christianity in
China so the Chinese are very clear
about this that this is a foreign
import. It's it's a it's a um it's a
foreign religion that uh that needs to
be controlled. That's how the Chinese
see uh the various Abrahamic religions.
Um the two major ones at least. Uh so
the Chinese are aware of of the of the
missionary agenda. Uh in Nepal it seems
to be running riot mission the
missionary agenda. Lots of Nepales I
hear are converting to Christianity. The
same thing is happening in various parts
of India. industrial scale conversions
to Christianity done by missionaries.
Yeah. uh various parts of India they
have essentially wiped out the the
indigenous culture of the far east of
India very to a very large extent places
like
[Music]
misoram well not miseram is never
indigenous in the first place but um I
mean Nagaland it's happening in
Arunachal Pradesh also happening in
Manipur as well it's happening in Punjab
it's happening in various parts of south
India and so on so the question is why
are the American missionaries and other
missionaries is hellbent on converting
people. See, it's about control. It's
about control. It's not about uplifting
people and and taking them to heaven
instead of hell or anything. It's about
controlling people. What's happening is
that Christianity is receding from the
west. If you go to Europe, most people
no longer practice Christianity. When I
was a little kid and the pope would
visit Ireland, there will be millions of
people on the streets there to get a
glimpse of the pope. John Paul 2. Today,
if the pope were to visit Ireland,
nobody will come out on the streets.
That's how badly Christianity has
receded, lost ground in Europe. And when
people stop practicing Christianity, the
the church loses control over the
people. This is the religion of control.
So that's why they want new regions
where they can control, they can
establish control. So that's why they're
seeking India and they're sitting
seeking various parts of Asia. India I
think it's just running riot and doesn't
look like there's any government
oversight on this um on this industrial
scale demographic re-engineering of
India and it's also happening in other
parts of of Asia. It's been happening
for a long time and South Korea well
it's not a sovereign nation so there's
nothing they can do about
it. Okay. Krishna Ragunat
um from the Surinabies Netherlands says
what's the current status of research
into Arian migration and indigenous
arianism?
Um what's the current status?
Look, research is ongoing at various
stages in various domains. Um there's
been a big big breakthrough from the
perspective of linguistics which is the
recent decipherment of the Saraswati
Synindu script or the Indas Valley
script or the Harapan script done by Mr.
Barat Rao also known as Deam. So the
decipherment of the script is a crucial
piece of the puzzle in answering the
question about the origin of Hinduism
and the origin of the Sanskrit language.
Because what is the core claim? The
central claim in the Arian invasion
migration theory. The central claim in
the Arian invasion and migration theory
is that Sanskrit and Hinduism are
foreign to India. That's the central
claim. It was white-kinned barbaric
invaders who brought this foreign
language Sanskrit and the foreign
religion Hinduism into India and imposed
it on the natives the black-skinned
people. That's what they claim either by
force or by coercion or whatever. So the
central claim of of this theory is that
Hinduism and Sanskrit are foreign to
India. And then if that is the case then
the Saraspati Hindu script or the
industelli script should be a pre-arian
script right like a dravidian script
allegedly there are two races in India
arians and dravidians and if the arians
were foreigners then the indust valley
script harapan script Hindu script
should be a nonarian language which
means a dravidian
language so the dis the decipherment of
the script is the
key is is is is is a major step forward.
So what has what's been the
decipherment? So Mr. Barat Rah who
deciphered the script has demonstrated
that it is Vic Sanskrit. The script was
used to encode the Vic Sanskrit language
and he he has deciphered all the
inscriptions and they're all Sanskrit
inscriptions.
So if these seals, if these inscriptions
which are like between 3,000 to 6,000
years old, which is way before the
so-called arian
invasion, if if that's the time period
of these inscriptions, then it means
that Sanskrit existed in in India before
the ar invasion of migration, which
means that Srita is indigenous to India
and all these gods, the Rdra and what
else who are it's mainly RDRA in the in
these Sarasodi sinduh the seals. So RDRA
is Lord Shiva. We call him Shiva today,
right? He's the probably the central
Hindu deity, the primordial Hindu deity,
the only truly supernatural deity in
Hinduism, the one who was never born and
the one who will never die.
Right? So that's the the central deity
of Hinduism in some ways is a deity that
was worshiped in India long before any
ar invasion or migration happened. So
this completely
demolishes the Arian invasion or
migration theory. Now obviously this
decipherment it needs to be corroborated
by independent sources. So we'll wait
for that to happen. But the methodology
that that Baratra was used to decipher
the script it's it's uh it's watertight.
So and and you know he he has a
background in computer science and he's
used u cryptographic methods to decipher
this to to decipher the script as a
cryptogram. It's a mathematical meth
methodology. Uh you can't really play
with that. I mean you can't really fake
that and no linguist with a background
in linguistics but no background in
mathematics can challenge it. So that's
the situation. So it's a gigantic blow
to the uh Arian invasion or migration or
tourism or picnic myth. Huge huge u
blow. So that's the linguistic aspect.
Gigantic progress in there. When it
comes to the genetic aspect, well I'm
not sure what the status of genetic
research is. What we need to have is a
you know we want to have this census in
India. We're going to have a cast census
in India. Let's have a genetic sens
genetic census in India. Let's take
genetic samples of a few lakh Indians
and study them properly systematically
to understand our deep ancestry going
back tens of thousands of years, maybe
going back 50, 70,000
years. Once that is done, I can
guarantee you we will find that we are
the oldest non-African population on the
planet. But that is a claim I'm making
without evidence today. I know it's
true, but I don't have evidence to back
it up. So whenever this research is
done, it's going to prove that or it's
going to prove me wrong, whichever way
it works. So that's where we stand when
it comes to the state of research,
status of research into the Arian
invasion, migration, myth and indigenous
aranism. We are the indigenous Arians.
The only people on the planet who can
genuinely truthfully call themselves
Arya or Arian are us, the Indians, and
our
Persian relatives not far away. Nobody
else can call themselves Arian. Whoever
else calls themselves Arian is is
stealing our identity. It's it's a case
of identity theft. Anyhow,
next geopolitical Dubai says, "How
different um is today's diplomacy is
today's Indian diplomacy from Bharat's
diplomacy before the Turk invasion?"
It's an excellent question and I I wish
more people would think this way that we
have a certain state of affairs in India
today. We have a certain kind of
governance system. We have a certain set
of institutions in the country. We have
a certain way of doing diplomacy and
interacting with other foreign powers.
How was all of this done a thousand
years ago before the Turk invasion of
India? I wish more people would wonder
about these things. So, how different is
today's diplomacy compared to before the
invasions? Well, first of all, we don't
have any
records from before the Turk invasions.
Whatever records may have existed would
have been destroyed in the destruction
of the universities and libraries of
India. when it comes to ancient
diplomacy
um if you if you see Egypt no longer
exists as a culture or civilization
today it's part of the Arab world today
but we still have records of their
diplomacy in the in the form of letters
and correspondence between Egypt and
various other powers in the region like
the Hittites like the Mitani and so on
um who was the Mitani king I think it
Tesharat or Dasharat who maintained a
long correspondence with one of the
Egyptian kings
pharaohs and uh one of I think his
sister was married to the Egyptian king
and his daughter was also married to the
Egyptian king and he had a long
correspondence ongoing correspondence
with the Egyptian king. He sends the
letter. The Egyptian king sends the
letter back. And then there's this reply
and there's another reply. And all of
that was was discovered in Egypt. And
after the Egyptian Pharaoh dies, uh the
the the Mitani king, Tesharat, continued
the correspondence with the king's
widow.
And it is a it's interesting
correspondence because the Mitani king
is kind of greedy and he wants some of
the gold that is said to be very
copiously available in Egypt. you have
gold like we have dust on the streets.
So why don't you send me some you know
you had promised that you would send me
some gold when are you going to send it
to me? That was a gest of the
correspondence
ongoing. So that's how diplomacy was
done between Egypt and uh various uh
neighboring
powers. So we have records that have
survived. We have records that survive
from Mesopotamia that region as well. We
have records that survive from Rome and
other countries in Europe. But in India,
the ancient records have been destroyed.
We have some understanding of of
diplomacy because of the correspondence
that seems to have uh survived between
um between uh so we know that you
know during the morian era u before the
morals we had a different dynasty
different empire that was in power in
India. There was the Nanda Empire and
when Alexander the Greek tried to invade
India, you he came face to face almost
face to face with the full might of the
Nanda Empire and his soldiers mutinied
and they refused to go forward further
into India and they uh forced Alexander
to go back to Babylon where he
died and just a few years later when his
general Salucas Nicer came to India
there's a whole new empire in place
which is the Moria Empire. So the Linda
Empire was destroyed by Chundra Gupta
Moria and Vishnut Tanaka and they set up
a new empire. Chundra Gupta became the
uh emperor of India, one of our great
emperors. And Salucas Niger, he
conducted a small brief war with India
at the time. It was not a very uh
serious war. It was kind of
half-hearted. And at the end of the war,
there was a treaty that was agreed upon.
It was a peace treaty between India and
Greece some two 2,300 something years
ago. So that was a negotiated peace
agreement. It was a negotiated alliance.
India and the solucid empire became
allies and we provided Salucas nicator
500 war elephants with um their drivers
Mahawats and in exchange for that Sucus
Nicator gave back whatever territories
he had he or Alexander or whoever had
taken. So we got back all of Gandhara
and all of that all the way to Persia.
So we so we got a good amount of our
territory back and we got a stable
border and we got friendship and we got
an alliance. So there was diplomacy that
happened here right but we don't have
the records of the proceedings who who
went and negotiated what was it Chandra
Chandra Gupta himself will not obviously
go he will have a foreign minister or a
prime minister who will negotiate on his
behalf. Was it Vishnopta Chanik who did
that? Was it somebody else? Who was the
negotiator from the Greek side? See, all
of that is lost. But we clearly did
diplomacy and it was a pretty good
strong agreement alliance that we u uh
that we agreed upon with the Greeks and
it lasted generations. So after Chandra
Gupta dies, after Sucus dies, Chandra
Gupta's son and Salucas's son continue
the same partnership and relationship
and they have correspondence apparently
that is also pretty friendly in warm. So
it was a treaty that that lasted at
least one generation more if not if not
more after that the solucid empire
itself disintegrated while the morian
empire continued under rashok and so on
so forth so I think the treaty lasted as
long as the solucid empire lasted so we
had excellent diplomacy at the time but
I'm not sure how it was conducted
uh we obviously were aware of u you know
of all the other kingdoms and empires in
the world uh it's not like we were
isolated with but uh we don't have the
records anymore. So it would be great if
our historians would try and investigate
these things instead of wasting the time
on god knows what you
know. Okay. Mr. 88 says back in the days
during the Moria Gupta and Chola empires
how did how much did international
relations matter? Very similar question
like today if you don't appreciate or
please uh US wishes you face the fear of
sanctions. So what kind of leverage did
the Indian empires have over other
nations back in the day? Uh what sort of
hard power did we use on others? Okay,
that's an interesting question. So um
how much did international relations
matter 2 and a half thousand years ago?
International relations did matter. Um
like I just said, we had excellent
relations. We had a treaty, you know, an
alliance with the Seucid Empire and the
Seucid Empire gained a lot as a
consequence of this treaty. He gained um
cutting edge weaponry you know war
elephants with mahads and using that
silucus negative was able to carve a
gigantic pretty gigantic empire uh for
himself and if you look at Ashoka's
inscriptions one of our greatest
emperors Ashoke and you will see that he
was aware of of who was ruling Egypt at
the time so um before Ashoke came his
father Bindusar before Binduar came
Ashok's grandfather Chandra Gupta Moria
And before Chandra Gupta Moria was a
different uh dynasty which was the Nanda
dynasty. Now during the Nanda period
Alexander the Greek tried to invade
India while he was on his way to India
before he conquered Persia. He had
conquered Egypt. He didn't conquer
Egypt. He just walked into Egypt and the
Egyptians allowed him to walk in because
they were at because at the time Egypt
was a vasal of Persia and the Egyptians
thought that Alexander is a is is a is a
is is bringing freedom to us. Well, it
didn't quite work that way. Alexander
installed a governor called
Tommy in Greece uh in in in Egypt. And
after Alexander died, Tomy's descendants
became the kings of
Egypt. Okay. So during Ashok's time
there was a king called Tommy in Greece
and in Ashok's inscriptions he's
referred to as Tulameay in Greece in in
Egypt. So our emperors were aware of
what was happening in Egypt. They would
have been aware of what was happening
elsewhere also in the world. It's not
like we were isolated insulated. We know
we knew what was happening in various
parts of the world. But those days we
did not have the speed of transportation
and communication that we have today. So
things were different at the time and
far away things didn't matter as much as
they do today. Today the US sitting
wherever they are they can rule
essentially the whole world right and
they can control the world and influence
the world. those days Egypt could not
influence or control India and we could
not do the same thing vice versa except
by you know by far away means
uh uh that's how it was and during the
Roman time Rome used to complain that
they were you know giving away all their
gold to India because uh the Roman
population was very fond of Indian
spices which were the best spices in the
world and they would spend fortunes
purchasing spices for from India which
would come from thousands of kilometers
way by by the sea road or land or
whichever maybe a mixture of both. So
India was was draining the wealth the
gold of Rome. So you had international
relations you had trade relations
international relations happened through
trade through warfare through many other
means uh during the Gupta
Empire also we you know these things
mattered. So for example when the Gupta
when the Gupta Empire started rising it
it arose out of Magad out of Patutra the
first Gupta king was
Kodkach who was based out of Patipudra
if I'm not mistaken if if my memory
serves be right and the the initial base
of the the Gupta Empire was partly it
was a Bihari empire Magadan empire
um and then eventually they started uh
they were able to conquer the whole of
the subcontinent and more and more even
Bahalik which
is Gandharbakistan that region and so
on. Uh so during that time when the
Gupta when the Gupta Empire was rising
it had not yet taken over the whole of
India at that time you had the
Mahakshhatraas the western shatrups who
were ruling in western India Gujarat
mainly and they were fabulously wealthy
because they controlled the ports that
traded with the west. So that in those
days it was the western poles in Gujarat
in western India that were the the hubs
of trade with Rome and Egypt and uh
Mesopotamia and so on and they were
fabulously wealthy as a consequence. And
so the Gupta I think it was which Gupta
empire was it? Was it Chandra Gupta?
probably Chandra Gupta who finally ended
the the rule of the Mahakshhatraas and
took over Gujarat and took over these
ports and the and the and the great
shrine of Sumnat and so on and that was
a great source of wealth not the shrine
of Sumat but the ports you see so
international relations mattered they
really did matter during the Chola
Empire international relations mattered
the Shirija Empire was misrepresenting
its relationship with the Cholas to
China and the Cholas launched a maritime
invasion of Shri
Vijaya. How far is Shri Vijaya?
Indonesia. Have you seen the map? So
they were able to launch a maritime
invasion and conquer Shijaya and
vasalize the whole of Southeast Asia all
the way to the Philippines in
incredible. So we had hard power. It's
very interesting. If you really study
history, you'll learn so much and you'll
be astonished as to what our ancestors
were capable of compared to what we are
capable of today.
Okay, Ritu um Run Ryar says why do
countries adopt other countries cultures
willingly like Russia and Japan
westernized and Southeast Asia
Indianized or Korea and Japan
sinusized? How does change of culture
happen? What's the process of change of
culture? This is a sociological
question. It's also a question that is
very integral to the study of history.
How does it happen? What's the process
of change? What's the mechanics and
dynamics of
change? Okay, I'll not um academize the
whole discussion. How does it happen?
Look, typically it's willingly or
unwillingly. Unwillingly, it's by the
sword. Like Islam has spread by the
sword. We know that, right? And
Christianity also has mostly spread by
the sword or through various other um
hard power means, right?
uh but there have been cases where
uh nations have adopted other cultures
willingly. In
what
circumstances would one culture adopt
another culture willingly? It can only
happen when the receptor culture
believes that the culture it is adopting
is
superior, genuinely superior. You will
only adopt somebody else's culture if
you believe it is genuinely better than
yours. That's the only way it happens
willingly. Right? So um Japan for
example the the Maji restoration in the
middle of the 18th uh sorry 19th
century mid 19th century onwards uh
Japan for a long time had this period of
isolationism. They were isolated and
they saw the might of the west the
gunboat diplomacy of the west. They saw
that the west had this technology and
they had this discipline and they were
barbaric the westerners but they were
going to win. So the Japanese decided
the the Japanese uh whoever was ruling
the elites they decided that we're going
to westernize Japan otherwise we we're
going to be wiped out. And so they
adopted western customs, western
culture, western education system,
everything western. They adopted
everything western and they very rapidly
westernized in a matter of decades.
That's called the maji restoration. and
they wiped out their samurai system as a
consequence and they tried to eradicate
Buddhism which
failed. So when you feel somebody else's
culture is better than yours and
superior to yours, you you then develop
an inferiority complex and you try to
change things and you may end up doing
harm to your own culture. So that's what
happened when the Japanese tried to
become westernized. They tried to wipe
out Buddhism which had been in Japan for
2,000 years nearly.
What happened to Southeast Asia? They
Indianized, right? Well, you will say
that when the Indian ind Indianization
happened, it it was a very long
process. The Indianization of Southeast
Asia began probably about 3,000 years
ago when merchants from Kolinga, today's
Orisa, were trading with Southeast Asia
with what was called Sarabumi, which is
Thailand, Indonesia, mostly Thailand,
the Thailand Cambodia region today. It's
called it was historically called Sov
Nabumi. Today the airport in Bangkok is
called Subaru Nabumi airport. So um
Indian traders, merchants, sailors would
go from Kolinga across the Bay of Bengal
and they which would be called the sea
of Kolinga actually and they would trade
with Sar Nabumi and over time the people
of Sur Nabumi Southeast Asia slowly
adopted Indian customs and culture and
they became
Hinduized. There was no force involved.
It was a period of it was it happened
over a very long period of centuries but
clearly they must have believed that
Indian culture is somehow superior to
theirs. So they adopted Indian culture
but they did not entirely lose their own
culture. Which is why if you go to
Southeast Asia whatever Hinduism is
still exists today. It's very localized.
It's a very very beautifully syncric
form of Hinduism. If you go to Bali it's
a very different form of Hinduism that
what you have in India. They worship the
same gods and goddesses but in their own
specific way. and they include they
incorporate a lot of their own ancient
practices in that. So that's the thing
about Hinduism everything is allowed. So
they were able to practice Hinduism in
their own way while not giving up many
elements of their own ancestral
practices. So that's how Indianization
happened. It was not by force and
probably the people of the region felt
that there is something of Indian
culture that they should adopt because
it is probably good. That's how it
happened. Japan and Korea sinusized
because of conquest. China was very
powerful at various points in time. It
was always a cyclical process. But you
see the the one of the characteristics
of a civilization is that it is a net
exporter of culture. So China was able
to export its culture to Vietnam to to
Korea and to some extent to Japan. And
China exported a lot of Indian culture
to Japan and and Korea. So a lot of
Indian culture came into Japan and Korea
through China in a in a in a Chinese in
a sinized way. Um yeah, that's what
happened. But the biggest exporter of
culture historically was India and we
are the opposite of that today. Now we
are a net importer of culture because
apparently it looks like our people
believe that you know western culture is
superior to ours today. The same process
is happening today in
reverse. Okay. Really now says how come
Shinto is closer to Hinduism than
Buddhism? What's the origin of Shinto?
Why is there no Shinto in other East
Asian countries? What are the
similarities between Shintoism and
Korean shamanists and the understanding
America chapters are over after that?
Let's do one more for East Asia, please.
Okay,
so yeah, I've said this, right? I have
said this that if you compare Shinto,
the native uh culture of Japan with
Hinduism and Buddhism, you'll find it
closer to Hinduism than to Buddhism.
And Japanese scholars wrote about this
about a thousand years ago that Shinto
is more akin to Hinduism than to
Buddhism. And they've criticized
Buddhism in some way or whatever. But
Buddhism took root in in Japan with a
lot of Hindu elements obviously because
it's the same thing overall. So um how
is Shinto closer to Hinduism than
Buddhism? What's the origin of Shinto?
First of all, the origin of Shinto is
the origin of the Japanese culture. It's
Japan's indigenous traditional
traditions and culture that's called
Shinto. It's socio religious cultural
practices. Uh there is there are
elements of nature worship in Shinto.
There are elements of ancestor worship
in Shinto. There are certain gods and
goddesses that the worship a whole
pantheon of gods and goddesses called
kami and so on. It's very similar to
Hinduism. See Buddhism it it emerges
some kind of reformation movement of
Hinduism. It became very popular for a
while in
India. Uh so Gautam Buddha wanted to
reform Hinduism and make it better. He
never said he was starting a new
religion. He said I am preaching you the
true meaning of dharma dharma. Right? So
he said that Hindu practice our
religious practices have become too uh
corrupted or whatever and I'm going to
show you the right way. And his way was
a more austere way and all that. Right?
So when it comes to Buddhism, it's like
a stripped down export ready variant of
Hinduism. That's what it is. That's what
Alan Watts said that Buddhism is
Hinduism stripped down for
export. Um so it's it's a much more
narrow narrower path in some ways.
Um very clear boundaries and and and
boundaries and delineations in Buddhism.
For example, you can't if you are a
Buddhist, you will not worship nature.
If you're a Buddhist, you will not
worship your
ancestors. True Buddhist, according to
the true doctrine of Buddhism, you don't
do all those things,
right? Uh but if you're a Hindu, you are
you are absolutely free to worship
nature. You absolutely free to worship
trees if you want. You can worship
forest spirits. You can worship
ancestral spirits. You can worship
animals and plants and birds if you
want. You can worship whatever you want
as a Hindu. That's the essence that even
Shinto has. So that's why it's closer to
classical Hinduism than to the export
version which is Buddhism, right? Um
what's the similarities between Shinto,
Tawoism, Koreanist? I'm not really sure
about that. Uh
Taoism, Towism I think it's a it's an
atheistic
uh system, isn't it?
Thoism if I'm not mistaken. I don't
remember very clearly right now but I
think Taoism doesn't have the belief in
God in Taoism. Korean shamanists once
again I'm not really sure. Shamanists
they typically are nature and ancestor
worshippers. So there will be
significant similarities between
shamanism and Shinto. Also the Mongolian
system which is called in English
Tangism. It's not a monotheistic
religion with the worship of one god
called Tangri. No, it's a whole pantheon
of gods. the sky father thing with the
earth mother Uma and and ancestor
spirits and nature spirits and whatnot.
It's a polytheistic uh system. So it's
it's in some ways similar to Hinduism
and and Shinto as well. So yeah, it's a
fascinating question actually and it's
really interesting to to study
this. Mr. 88 says, "Has time always been
uniform on this planet like the Earth
completing its one rotation in 24 hours?
Has it always been like this or the
duration of one rotation was different
in the past and could be different in
the future? Listen, in about 100 or 200
million years, the day on the planet
will be about 25 hours
long. 25 of today's hours long. In the
past, the day was
shorter. So what is one day? First of
all, let's understand what's one day.
One day is the time the planet takes to
rotate completely once around on its own
axis. So let's say this is my planet. It
goes around the sun like that. Let's say
this is the sun. So it goes around the
sun, right? But while going around the
sun, it also spins. Spins like legs spin
off spin whatever it spins, right? So
the time it takes to spin completely
360° that's one day.
Now when the planet was born the when
the earth was born when it was very new
about 4 and a half billion years ago uh
one period of rotation one 360° turn was
less than 10 hours most likely 5 to 10
hours in that
range. Then the moon was formed through
a giant impact most likely with another
planet and the ejecta coalesed to form
the moon and then because of tidal
friction the rotation period slowly
slowly
decreased and
about 70 million years ago uh the day
was about 23 or 23 and 1/2 hours long
around the time the dinosaurs were on
the last legs and today it's about 24
hours in 100 or 200 million years it
will be 25 or more hours. So the period
of rotation of the planet has always
been changing. It's it's it's slowing
it's it's gradually slowing down and the
moon is gradually going further away
from the earth and the earth is losing
its rotational
speed. Uh eventually in maybe about five
six billion years the earth may be tidly
tidily locked with the sun. So we always
see just one face of the moon right we
never see the other side of the moon
because the moon is tidily locked with
the earth and similarly in five or six
billion years the earth will be tidily
locked most likely with the sun which is
going to be the post red giant phase
which means the the oceans will have
boiled off by that time. Uh so so that's
how it has always been. Nothing is
constant in the universe and is time
constant on on each part on every part
of the
earth. The in this the center of the
earth the core of the earth is about 2
to three years younger than the surface
of the
earth. The core of the earth is about 2
to three years younger than the surface
of the earth because of gravitational
time dilation the gravitational red
shift.
Uh yeah that you can study if you study
relativity.
So okay ultimate power A1 says what's
the best martial art in the world for
real life combat also what Indian origin
martial art do you think can stand
global competition and deserves serious
recognition? I will not answer the last
part of the question because it will
generate enormous controversy
controversy and I have had enough
controversy for a while. So forget about
the last part of the question but which
is the best martial art in the world for
real life
combat.
Um I think there are two or three
martial arts that can fit the bill. One
is Krav Maga which is an Israeli martial
art. It's not a martial art for
competition. It's a martial art for the
street. In Krav Maga, you use anything
at your disposal and your objective is
not to win the
fight. It's to end the
guy. Okay? So, Kravaga is a real life
combat art martial art in which
everything goes. There are there are no
rules. Everything is allowed and the
objective is to quickly dispatch the
guy. So, Kra is really good at that.
There is one if you are talking about
martial arts in which you want to not
dispatch the guy or end the guy. I think
jiu-jitsu is great. Jiu-jitsu is
tremendous. People who are really I mean
if you're a fighter who is really good
at jiu-jitsu, you can defeat almost
anybody. Jiu-jitsu is great. Even
is great. is is a Japanese sorry
Russian martial art. It has elements of
wrestling, elements of you know
striking. Uh Fedor Ebanenko is was used
to be a Sambbo fighter and then he
became MMA fighter. So sambbo is also
great. Among the Chinese martial arts, I
would say sanchu or sa is is is pretty
good. It's it's a variant of kung
fu and u it it's it's somewhat
different. So I would say these are good
for real life combat. Probably the two
best uh the three best I would say are
kravaga and uh jiu-jitsu and
sambbo. Even karate is great. Actually
karate the real karat not not today's
karate. Today's karate is is a joke. the
the 20th century version of Karate, the
real Karati. That was great. Uh yeah,
that's my answer. Okay, let's take some
questions from the live chat now. I'll
I'll do it for about 10 minutes. So, in
case you have questions and you want to
ask me them in life, ask me now. Raava
Verodora says, "What's the purpose of
life?" Look, the purpose of life depends
on the person. Everybody has their own
should have their own definition of
what's the purpose of of life.
Um, from my
perspective, if I can give more to
society than I take from society in my
lifetime, then I think I've lived a
pretty good life. So, that's one way of
looking at it from my
perspective. Okay, what
next? Okay, Amisha says, "Did General
Dyer ever regret his actions?" I'm not
sure. I have I've really not read about
General Dyer, what his life was like and
what his writings were. I'm not sure if
he regretted his actions and I don't
care because whether he regretted or not
he did something heenous.
Yeah. Ananta Chandak says uh today's
karat is a joke. I black belt but still
well I'm glad you understand that.
Recognize that. Well, you can climb up
the ladder. Multiple don black belt
right. Maha says, "Is emotion an
integral path of consciousness? If yes,
how can AI be without flaws since
emotion is what causes
them? Okay, I'm not sure what's the
connection to AI. But first of all, the
first part of the question is emotion an
integral part of consciousness. Look, I
don't know uh from a scientific
perspective, we don't know what
consciousness is because why why do I
say we don't know what it is? It's
because we don't have a scientific
definition of consciousness. Look, I
have a scientific definition of a
sphere.
I have scientific definitions for
everything I can observe, measure,
quantify. Every phenomenon that I can
observe, I can define that
scientifically because I have data.
Consciousness, it's it's something
strange. When when I see this ball, I
know there's no consciousness
here. When I see an animal, I know
there's consciousness there. So when you
see it, you recognize it immediately. So
it exists. But what is it? How can I
define it from let's say a physics
perspective? I have no idea. How do I
define it from a neurological
perspective? Neuroscience perspective. I
don't know. How do I define it from a
biological perspective? I don't know. No
one knows. It's one of the biggest
mysteries in science. It's something
that exists. We recognize it immediately
when we see it. But science from a
science scientific perspective, we don't
know how to define it. Let's say I have
a black box containing a consciousness.
What are the characteristics that this
consciousness will have? That's a good
starting point actually to start. And we
can use information theory to get into
it and so on. Uh is emotion an integral
part of
consciousness? So emotions are are
essentially these these feelings. How do
you define emotions?
Emotions are reactions, aren't
they? To something that happens either
externally or
internally. These are reactions.
So you could describe any reaction as
some kind of emotion perhaps. Not sure.
Yeah. These are very fuzzy
topics. If if if you are conscious and
you respond and react in some fashion to
things that happen either externally or
internally and if you can define that as
an emotion then it should be an internal
part of consciousness. Yes. Now if yes,
how can AI be without flaws? Because
emotion causes flaws.
But the question is, is AI
conscious? Right? That's the that's the
question. What is consciousness? Once
again, that that's what we have to ask.
And is AI conscious? We don't have the
answers. We don't know whether today's
AIs are conscious or not. Whether
whether they are
semiconscious, they certainly pass the
touring test. You can't tell whether
that's a human being or or a machine on
the other side. It can speak with you
and communicate with you just like a
human being would. It can even even
pretend like it has it has
emotions. But does it really have
emotions?
Um it's possible they may have some some
level of consciousness which would be
very sad actually but yeah so so the
answer is we don't have answers as of
today. All right. Okay. What else do we
have? P questions. I've answered them
enough. Okay. Answered enough P
questions. When are they taking back P?
Patience.
Um, geopolitical Dubai points out a
shocking occurrence in today's episode.
I haven't opened the map
yet. You're right. How did that happen?
I think it's because we discussed
Pakistan mostly, right? Pakistan, we all
know the map. Yeah. Yeah. There, this is
probably the first episode in which I
have not opened the map. In which case,
I should do something about it. Where is
map? I shall open it just just for the
sake of opening the map because how can
there be an episode without the map on
the
screen? So here we have the map. Here's
the map of the world. Check it out. Yes.
Thank you sir for reminding me that I
haven't opened the map yet and now that
is done and now it is a complete
episode. All right, let's see some other
questions.
Um, unknown says, "I'm passionate about
art, drawing and painting. A map. I'm a
aiming for a BF, a Bachelor of Fine Arts
at the College of Art, Delhi. What other
courses or careers should I consider in
India or abroad? Look, I don't have a
background in arts. I used to be an avid
drawer and painter as a kid. I was
really good at drawing like really good.
Uh, I
probably possibly could have been an
artist if I wanted to. So listen, I
don't have any uh understanding of what
is the path forward
academically for any person as an artist
as an artist. Um so I I'm not the right
person to uh to uh to ask this question.
BFA is bachelor of fine arts. I know
that um look being an artist I think
it's easier today uh in India than
before because in the past people had no
wealth, no money and they had no time
for art. Today people have the time to
go as tourists to various parts of of
the country and other parts of the
world. People have the time to visit art
galleries, even buy art pieces. So it's
it's easier uh to be an artist today.
It's it's more uh viable of a career
than it was 20 years ago. uh but you
have to be good at it and then you need
to do the right things and play the play
the right the game the right way I
suppose uh what other courses can you
can you consider in India or abroad I'm
not sure
um I'm not sure I'm not the not the
right person to ask but uh you know you
can be an artist in in residence at
various art galleries in the world you
to apply for that you have to show your
portfolio you need to be good at what
you're doing in which case you can
become an artist in residence artist in
residence in various art galleries maybe
for a six month tenure one year or
something and I'm sure there are courses
that uh various universities, colleges
offer outside of this country, maybe
even in this country. Uh but the main
thing is that um being an artist is
difficult. If you're good then you can
make it work especially in today's age
when you have Instagram and you have you
can showcase your portfolio online and
all that. So, it's it's much more of a
practical uh career choice than it was
20 30 years ago. That's the best I can
tell you. I'm not the right person for
advice on a career in art, but I wish
you all the best,
sir. Right. Okay. Let's see some more
questions. Harry Koshel says, "How to
get rich?" Listen, give society what
they want and what they can't get. And
if you can do that at scale like Naval
says, you'll get
rich. Uh Govinda Modelikar says, "How do
you see chemical engineer as a career in
India? Where can be its future?" The
career its future is in industry. Uh
India is going to is is increasingly
becoming a nation that is a
manufacturing oriented nation and
economy. in that you need chemical
engineering. So in any industry you're
going to have some need for chemicals
and chemical engineering processes and
all that. So I think it's a pretty good
solid career choice if you want to be a
chemical engineer. Plenty of industries
uh need chemical engineers. So that's
what I can
say. Mahesh partle says tomorrow is my
neat exam. Wish me luck. All the best.
All the best Mahesh. do well and yes
succeed. All the
best. Right.
Okay.
Um Mr. 88 says what type of artist you
wanted to become. S I never wanted to be
an
artist. Artist was just art was just a
hobby. I enjoyed it. I used to enjoy
drawing, painting, coloring, sketching,
all that. Other
arts, music.
Yes, I am a very artistic person, but I
have never considered art as a choice,
as a career choice. But yeah, it's fun.
It's it's it's a good way to unwind and,
you know,
um unwind and relax and all that by
indulging in some hobby, especially if
you're reasonably good at it. And I'm
reasonably good at this stuff. So,
yeah. Uh okay. What
else? Uh any other interesting
questions? Let us see. Let us
see. I don't know what to take. I've
taken these questions before. Okay.
Let's see this podcast of Punjabi. Oh,
podcast G. Oh, Punjabi G. I'm from
Punjab. Do you do you farming nowadays?
No. What is I am from Punjab. Do you
farming nowadays profitable business or
farmers need
to is farming a profitable business
today? I think farming can be profitable
it can be lucrative. I think about half
of India's workforce is in is involved
in in agriculture in some way. You know
if we become a proper technology
oriented nation and we bring in
industrial tools in farming then we can
make it even more profitable and even
more productive. So if you have a decent
amount of land, if if and if you use the
right equipment, etc., farming can be
really profitable. Yes, it
can. Uh, all right, with that, I'm going
to end today's session. 2 hours 15
minutes as always. So, thank you so much
everybody for all your questions. It was
fun taking them. It was fun doing the
live chat as well. And I will see you in
a week's time, same time, same channel
next week. Until then, take care, keep
asking questions, keep learning all the
time, and keep raising your standards.
Thank you very much, and I'll see you
very soon. Bye-bye.